I have a confession to make.
أود البوح بأمر ما.
I'm a business professor
أنا أستاذة أعمال
whose ambition has been to help people learn to lead.
تطمح لمساعدة الناس لتعلم القيادة.
But recently, I've discovered
لكني اكتشفت مؤخرًا
that what many of us think of as great leadership
أن مفهوم القيادة الناجحة لدى العديد منا
I'm an ethnographer.
أنا متمرسة في الإثنوغرافيا.
I use the methods of anthropology
وأستعمل مناهج علم الأنثربولوجيا
to understand the questions in which I'm interested.
لفهم المسائل التي أهتم بها.
So along with three co-conspirators,
لذلك قضيت برفقة 3 من زملائي
I spent nearly a decade observing up close and personal
ما يقرب العقد في مراقبة قادة الابتكار
exceptional leaders of innovation.
الاستثنائيين عن كثب.
We studied 16 men and women,
درسنا 16 رجل وامرأة،
located in seven countries across the globe,
متواجدين في 7 دول حول العالم،
working in 12 different industries.
ويعملون في 12 مجال مختلف.
In total, we spent hundreds of hours on the ground,
وفي المجمل، قضينا مئات الساعات نراقب
on-site, watching these leaders in action.
أولئك القادة أثناء ممارسة عملهم.
We ended up with pages and pages and pages of field notes
وانتهينا بملاحظات ميدانية هائلة
that we analyzed and looked for patterns in what our leaders did.
قمنا بتحليلها وبحثنا فيها عن أنماط
The bottom line?
لسلوكيات القادة. خلاصة القول؟
If we want to build organizations that can innovate time and again,
إن أردنا إنشاء منظمات قادرة على الابتكار باستمرار
we must unlearn our conventional notions of leadership.
علينا نسيان مفاهيمنا التقليدية للقيادة.
Leading innovation is not about creating a vision,
قيادة الابتكار لا تتعلق بخلق رؤية،
and inspiring others to execute it.
وإلهام الآخرين على تنفيذها.
But what do we mean by innovation?
لكن ما الذي نعنيه بالابتكار؟
An innovation is anything that is both new and useful.
الابتكار هو أي شيء جديد ومفيد.
It can be a product or service.
وقد يكون منتج أو خدمة.
It can be a process or a way of organizing.
أو عملية تنظيمية أو أسلوب تنظيمي.
It can be incremental, or it can be breakthrough.
قد يكون شيء مُضاف أو شيء كاسح ومتقدم.
We have a pretty inclusive definition.
لدينا تعريف شامل جدَّا.
How many of you recognize this man?
كم منكم من يعرف هذا الرجل؟
Put your hands up.
ارفعوا أيديكم.
Keep your hands up, if you know who this is.
ابقوها مرفوعة إن كنتم تعرفون هذا الرجل.
How about these familiar faces?
ماذا عن هذه الوجوه المألوفة؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
From your show of hands,
من خلال أيديكم المرفوعة،
it looks like many of you have seen a Pixar movie,
يبدو أن أكثركم قد شاهد أحد أفلام بيكسار،
but very few of you recognized Ed Catmull,
لكن قليل منكم كان يعرف إد كاتمول،
the founder and CEO of Pixar --
المؤسس والرئيس التنفيذي لشركة بيكسار،
one of the companies I had the privilege of studying.
واحدة من الشركات التي تشرفت بدراستها.
My first visit to Pixar was in 2005,
زيارتي الأولى لبيكسار كانت عام 2005،
when they were working on "Ratatouille,"
عندما كانوا يعملون على فيلم Ratatouille
that provocative movie about a rat becoming a master chef.
ذلك الفيلم المثير حول جرذ يصبح طاهيًا.
Computer-generated movies are really mainstream today,
الأفلام المستحدثة بالحاسوب هي الدارجة اليوم
but it took Ed and his colleagues nearly 20 years
لكن إد ورفاقه قضوا 20 عام تقريبًا
to create the first full-length C.G. movie.
لإنتاج أول فيلم طويل مستحدث بالحاسوب.
In the 20 years hence, they've produced 14 movies.
وفي العشرين عام التالية، أنتجوا 14 فيلم.
I was recently at Pixar, and I'm here to tell you
كنت مؤخرًا في بيكسار، وأنا هنا لأخبركم
that number 15 is sure to be a winner.
أن الفلم رقم 15 سيكون كاسحًا بلا شك.
When many of us think about innovation, though,
لكن عندما يفكر أكثرنا بالابتكار،
we think about an Einstein having an 'Aha!' moment.
يخطر لنا آنشتاين وهو يعيش لحظة تجلي.
But we all know that's a myth.
لكننا نعلم جميعًا أن هذه خرافة.
Innovation is not about solo genius,
الابتكار لا يتعلق بالعبقرية المنفردة،
it's about collective genius.
إنما بالعبقرية الجماعية.
Let's think for a minute about what it takes to make a Pixar movie:
لنفكر للحظة بما يتطلبه إنتاج أفلام بيكسار:
No solo genius, no flash of inspiration produces one of those movies.
ما من عبقرية فردية أو ومضة إلهام تنتج تلك الأفلام.
On the contrary, it takes about 250 people four to five years,
على العكس، يقضى 250 شخص 5-4 سنوات
to make one of those movies.
لإنتاج واحدة من تلك الأفلام.
To help us understand the process,
ولكي نفهم العملية،
an individual in the studio drew a version of this picture.
رسم عامل في الاستوديو نسخة من هذه الصورة.
He did so reluctantly,
وفعل ذلك على مضض
because it suggested that the process was a neat series of steps
لأن ذلك يظهر أن العملية منظمة
done by discrete groups.
نفذتها مجموعات منفصلة.
Even with all those arrows, he thought it failed to really tell you
حتى مع كل تلك الأسهم، كان يظن أنه أخفق في
just how iterative, interrelated and, frankly, messy their process was.
إخباركم كيف كانت العملية مترابطة وفوضوية.
Throughout the making of a movie at Pixar, the story evolves.
وتتطور القصة خلال صناعة الفيلم في بيكسار،
So think about it.
فكروا بذلك.
Some shots go through quickly.
بعض اللقطات تؤدى سريعًا.
They don't all go through in order.
لا يتبعون نظامًا معينًا.
It depends on how vexing the challenges are
يعتمد الأمر على مدى صعوبة التحديات
that they come up with when they are working on a particular scene.
التي تظهر لهم خلال عملهم على مشهد معين.
So if you think about that scene in "Up"
لو فكرتم بذلك المشهد في فيلم Up
where the boy hands the piece of chocolate to the bird,
حين يعطي الصبي قطعة الشوكولاته للطائر،
that 10 seconds took one animator almost six months to perfect.
الثواني العشر تلك استغرقت الرسام ستة أشهر لإتمامها.
The other thing about a Pixar movie
الأمر الآخر حول بيكسار
is that no part of the movie is considered finished
أنه لا يُعد أي جزء في الفيلم منتهيًا
until the entire movie wraps.
حتى ينتهي الفيلم بالكامل.
Partway through one production, an animator drew a character
في أحد المرات رسم رسام شخصية .
with an arched eyebrow that suggested a mischievous side.
بحاجبين مقوسين يوحيان بالشر.
When the director saw that drawing, he thought it was great.
عندما رأى المدير ذلك الرسم، رأى أنه رائع.
It was beautiful, but he said,
كان جميلاً، لكنه قال:
"You've got to lose it; it doesn't fit the character."
"عليك أن تتخلص منه لأنه لا يلائم الشخصية."
Two weeks later, the director came back and said,
وبعد أسبوعين، عاد المدير وقال:
"Let's put in those few seconds of film."
"لنقحم تلك الثواني القليلة في الفيلم."
Because that animator was allowed to share
ولأنه كان مسموحًا للرسام مشاركة ما
what we referred to as his slice of genius,
نسميه جانبه العبقري،
he was able to help that director reconceive the character
فقد تمكن من جعل المدير يعيد النظر في الشخصية .
in a subtle but important way that really improved the story.
بطريقة حاذقة حسّنت من القصة.
What we know is, at the heart of innovation is a paradox.
ما نعرفه أن الابتكار في أساسه مفارقة.
You have to unleash the talents and passions of many people
يتطلب إطلاق العنان لمواهب الناس وشغفهم
and you have to harness them into a work that is actually useful.
واستغلال ذلك في عمل مفيد ونافع.
Innovation is a journey.
الابتكار عبارة عن رحلة.
It's a type of collaborative problem solving,
إنه نوع من حل المشكلات الجماعي،
usually among people who have different expertise
الذي يكون عادة بين أشخاص أصحاب خبرات
and different points of view.
ووجهات نظر مختلفة.
Innovations rarely get created full-blown.
نادرًا ما تنشأ الابتكارات من الوهلة الأولى
As many of you know,
فكما يعرف معظمكم،
they're the result, usually, of trial and error.
تأتي عادةً نتيجة التجربة والخطأ.
Lots of false starts, missteps and mistakes.
الكثير من البدايات والخطى الخاطئة والأخطاء
Innovative work can be very exhilarating,
العمل الابتكاري قد يكون عملاً مبهجًا،
but it also can be really downright scary.
لكنه أيضًا قد يكون مرعبًا تمامًا.
So when we look at why it is that Pixar is able to do what it does,
فعندما نبحث عن سبب قدرة بيكسار على ماتفعله
we have to ask ourselves, what's going on here?
علينا أن نسأل أنفسنا عمّا يجري هنا؟
For sure, history and certainly Hollywood,
بالتأكيد، التاريخ وحاليًّا هوليوود،
is full of star-studded teams that have failed.
يزخران بالفرق اللامعة التي أخفقت.
Most of those failures are attributed
وتعزى معظم تلك الإخفاقات
to too many stars or too many cooks, if you will, in the kitchen.
لكثرة النجوم أو الطهاة في المطبخ إن شئتم.
So why is it that Pixar, with all of its cooks,
لماذا إذن بيكسار بكل نجومها
is able to be so successful time and time again?
قادرة على تحقيق النجاح باستمرار؟
When we studied an Islamic Bank in Dubai,
عندما درسنا إحدى المصارف الإسلامية في دبي،
or a luxury brand in Korea, or a social enterprise in Africa,
أو العلامات التجارية الفاخرة في كوريا أو المشاريع الاجتماعية في أفريقيا،
we found that innovative organizations
وجدنا بأن المنظمات الابتكارية
are communities that have three capabilities:
هي مجتمعات تمتلك 3 قدرات:
creative abrasion, creative agility and creative resolution.
التجريد الإبداعي والمرونة الإبداعية والقرار الإبداعي
Creative abrasion is about being able to create a marketplace of ideas
التجريد الإبداعي متعلق بالقدرة على خلق ميدان للأفكار
through debate and discourse.
من خلال النقاش والحوار.
In innovative organizations, they amplify differences,
المنظمات الإبداعية توسع الاختلافات
they don't minimize them.
ولا تصغرها.
Creative abrasion is not about brainstorming,
لا يتعلق التجريد الإبداعي بالعصف الذهني،
where people suspend their judgment.
حيث يضع الأشخاص حدًّا لحكمهم.
No, they know how to have very heated but constructive arguments
لا، إنها تعرف كيف تخلق جدالات حامية لكنها بناءة
to create a portfolio of alternatives.
لإنشاء ملف من البدائل.
Individuals in innovative organizations
يتعلم الأفراد في المنظمات الإبتكارية
learn how to inquire, they learn how to actively listen, but guess what?
كيف يسألون ويستمعون جيدًا، لكن خمنوا ماذا؟
They also learn how to advocate for their point of view.
إنهم يتعلمون أيضًا كيف يدافعون عن آرائهم.
They understand that innovation rarely happens
إنهم يدركون أن الابتكار لا يحدث
unless you have both diversity and conflict.
إلا بوجود التنوع والاختلاف.
Creative agility is about being able to test and refine that portfolio of ideas
المرونة الإبداعية تتعلق بالقدرة على تجريب الأفكار وصقلها
through quick pursuit, reflection and adjustment.
من خلال الممارسة السريعة والاستبصار والتكييف.
It's about discovery-driven learning
إنها ترتبط بالمعرفة المدفوعة بالاكتشاف
where you act, as opposed to plan, your way to the future.
حيث تسلك الطريق نحو المستقبل خلافًا للخطة.
It's about design thinking where you have that interesting combination
إنها ترتبط بالتفكير التصميمي حيث يوجد ذلك المزيج الرائع
of the scientific method and the artistic process.
بين الطريقة العلمية والعملية الفنية.
It's about running a series of experiments, and not a series of pilots.
إنها متعلقة بإجراء مجموعة من التجارب وليس مجموعة من المخططات.
Experiments are usually about learning.
والتجارب عادةً ما تتربط بالتعلم.
When you get a negative outcome,
حيث أنك لو حصلت على نتيجة سلبية
you're still really learning something that you need to know.
فأنت لا تزال تتعلم شيئًا يلزمك معرفته.
Pilots are often about being right.
الخطط غالبًا لا تحتمل وجود الأخطاء،
When they don't work, someone or something is to blame.
فلو لم تنجح، لابد وأن يلام أحد أو شيء ما.
The final capability is creative resolution.
القدرة الأخيرة هي القرار الإبداعي.
This is about doing decision making
وهي ترتبط بصنع القرارات
in a way that you can actually combine even opposing ideas
بطريقة تمكنك من دمج الأفكار المتعارضة أيضًا
to reconfigure them in new combinations
لإعادة تشكيلها في تراكيب جديدة
to produce a solution that is new and useful.
وإنتاج حل جديد ومفيد.
When you look at innovative organizations, they never go along to get along.
لو نظرت للمنظمات الابتكارية تجد أن أفرادها
They don't compromise.
لا يسايرون بعضهم ولا يجرون تسويات.
They don't let one group or one individual dominate,
لا يدعون الهيمنة لمجموعة واحدة أو لفرد،
even if it's the boss, even if it's the expert.
حتى لو كان الرئيس أو المختص.
Instead, they have developed
بدلاً من ذلك، طوروا
a rather patient and more inclusive decision making process
عملية صنع قرار متلقية وأكثر شمولية
that allows for both/and solutions to arise
تتيح لظهور الحلول المشتقة من كل طرف
and not simply either/or solutions.
وليس حلول إما/أو.
These three capabilities are why we see
تلك القدرات الثلاث هي سبب
that Pixar is able to do what it does.
تمكّن شركة بيسكار من فعل ما تفعله الآن.
Let me give you another example,
سأذكر لكم مثالاً آخر.
and that example is the infrastructure group of Google.
وهو لمجموعة البنية التحتية لشركة جوجل،
The infrastructure group of Google is the group
مجموعة البنية التحتية في جوجل
that has to keep the website up and running 24/7.
مسؤولة عن إبقاء الموقع في حالة تشغيل.
So when Google was about to introduce Gmail and YouTube,
عندما أوشكت جوجل على إطلاق جيميل ويوتيوب
they knew that their data storage system wasn't adequate.
كانت تعلم أن نظامها لتخزين البيانات لم يكن ملائمًا
The head of the engineering group and the infrastructure group at that time
رئيس مجموعة الهندسة ومجموعة البنية التحتية في ذلك الوقت
was a man named Bill Coughran.
كان رجلاً يدعى بيل كوران.
Bill and his leadership team, who he referred to as his brain trust,
بيل وفريقه القيادي الذي كان يسميه هيئة الخبراء،
had to figure out what to do about this situation.
كان عليهم أن يتوصلوا لحل هذه المشكلة.
They thought about it for a while.
استغرق منهم التفكير فترة من الوقت.
Instead of creating a group to tackle this task,
وبدلاً من إنشاء مجموعة لتولي هذه المهمة،
they decided to allow groups to emerge spontaneously
قرروا السماح للمجموعات بالظهور تلقائيًّا
around different alternatives.
حول بدائل مختلفة.
Two groups coalesced.
اندمجت مجموعتان.
One became known as Big Table,
عُرفت الأولى بـ"الطاولة الكبيرة".
the other became known as Build It From Scratch.
والثانية بـ "أنشأه من لا شيء"
Big Table proposed that they build on the current system.
اقترحت الأولى الاعتماد على النظام الحالي.
Build It From Scratch proposed that it was time for a whole new system.
واقترحت الثانية إنشاء نظام جديد كليًّا.
Separately, these two teams were allowed to work full-time
سُمح للفريقين العمل منفصليَن بدوام كامل
on their particular approach.
كلٌّ بأسلوبه الخاص.
In engineering reviews, Bill described his role as,
في مراجعات الهندسة، وصف بيل دوره بـ
"Injecting honesty into the process by driving debate."
"إدخال النزاهة في العملية بقيادة النقاش."
Early on, the teams were encouraged to build prototypes so that they could
وقد تم حث الفريقين على بناء نماذج تجريبية ليتمكنوا من
"bump them up against reality and discover for themselves
"تجربتها في الواقع ويكتشفوا بأنفسهم
the strengths and weaknesses of their particular approach."
نقاط القوة والضعف لأسلوبهم الخاص."
When Build It From Scratch shared their prototype with the group
عندما شاركت المجموعة الثانية نموذجها التجريبي مع المجموعة
whose beepers would have to go off in the middle of the night
التي كانت منبهاتها تنطلق في منتصف الليل،
if something went wrong with the website,
عندما يحدث خطأ ما في الموقع،
they heard loud and clear about the limitations of their particular design.
أدركوا تمامًا أوجه القصور في تصميمهم.
As the need for a solution became more urgent
وبما أن الحاجة للحل أصبحت أكثر إلحاحًا
and as the data, or the evidence, began to come in,
وبما أن البيانات بدأت في الدخول،
it became pretty clear that the Big Table solution
أصبح واضحًا تمامًا أن حل "الطاولة الكبيرة"
was the right one for the moment.
كان هو الحل المناسب لتلك اللحظة.
So they selected that one.
فاختاروا ذلك الحل.
But to make sure that they did not lose the learning
لكن ولكي يتأكدوا أنهم لم يفوّتوا تعلمهم
of the Build it From Scratch team,
من فريق "أنشأها من لا شيء"،
Bill asked two members of that team to join a new team that was emerging
طلب بيل من عضوين الانضمام إلى فريق جديد
to work on the next-generation system.
كان ناشئًا للعمل على نظام الجيل التالي.
This whole process took nearly two years,
استغرقت تلك العملية بأكملها عامين تقريبًا
but I was told that they were all working at breakneck speed.
لكن قيل لي أنهم كانوا يعملون بسرعة هائلة.
Early in that process, one of the engineers had gone to Bill and said,
وفي وقت مبكر من العملية، ذهب أحد المهندسين
"We're all too busy for this inefficient system
إلى بيل وقال:"كلنا لا نملك الوقت لنظام
of running parallel experiments."
إجراء التجارب المتوازية غير الفعال."
But as the process unfolded, he began to understand
ولكن مع انكشاف العملية، بدأ يدرك
the wisdom of allowing talented people to play out their passions.
الحكمة من السماح للموهوبين بالكشف عن شغفهم
He admitted, "If you had forced us to all be on one team,
حيث اعترف:"لو جعلتنا نركز على فريق واحد،
we might have focused on proving who was right, and winning,
كنا سنركز على إثبات الصواب والفوز
and not on learning and discovering what was the best answer for Google."
وليس على التعلم واكتشاف الحل الأمثل لجوجل."
Why is it that Pixar and Google are able to innovate time and again?
ما سبب قدرة بيكسار وجوجل على الابتكار دائمًا؟
It's because they've mastered the capabilities required for that.
لأنهم تفوقوا في القدرات اللازمة لذلك.
They know how to do collaborative problem solving,
إنهم يجيدون الحل الجماعي للمشكلات.
they know how to do discovery-driven learning
ويجيدون القيام بالتعلم المدفوع بالاكتشاف،
and they know how to do integrated decision making.
وصناعة القرارت المتكاملة.
Some of you may be sitting there and saying to yourselves right now,
بعضكم قد يجلس هناك ويقول لنفسه:
"We don't know how to do those things in my organization.
."لكننا لا نعرف كيف نطبق هذا في منظماتنا.
So why do they know how to do those things at Pixar,
لماذا يعرفون كيفية تطبيق ذلك في بيكسار،
and why do they know how to do those things at Google?"
ولماذا يعرفون كيفية تطبيق ذلك في جوجل؟"
When many of the people that worked for Bill told us,
عندما أخبرنا عديد ممن يعمل لدى بيل
in their opinion, that Bill was one of the finest leaders in Silicon Valley,
أنه برأيهم أحد أميز القادة في وادي السيليكون،
we completely agreed; the man is a genius.
وافقناهم تمامًا. الرجل عبقري.
Leadership is the secret sauce.
القيادة هي المكوّن السري.
But it's a different kind of leadership,
لكنها نوع مختلف من القيادة،
not the kind many of us think about when we think about great leadership.
وليس ذلك النوع الذي يخطر ببالنا عند التفكير بالقيادة.
One of the leaders I met with early on said to me,
أحد القادة الذين التقيت بهم قال لي:
"Linda, I don't read books on leadership.
"ليندا، أنا لا أقرأ الكتب المتعلقة بالقيادة.
All they do is make me feel bad." (Laughter)
إنها تشعرني بالسوء. (ضحك)
"In the first chapter they say I'm supposed to create a vision.
"تذكر في الفصل الأول أن عليّ أن أنشيء رؤية.
But if I'm trying to do something that's truly new, I have no answers.
لكن لو كنت أفعل شييئًا جديد كليًّا فلا أملك إجابات
I don't know what direction we're going in
لا أعرف الوجهة التي نذهب صوبها.
and I'm not even sure I know how to figure out how to get there."
كما أني غير متأكد من معرفتي بالطريقة التي توصلني إليها."
For sure, there are times when visionary leadership
بالتأكيد، القيادة ذات الرؤية تكون هي
is exactly what is needed.
ما يلزم بالتحديد في بعض الأوقات.
But if we want to build organizations that can innovate time and again,
لكن لو أردنا إنشاء منظمات قادرة على الابتكار المستمر،
we must recast our understanding of what leadership is about.
فعلينا إعادة صياغة فهمنا لماهية القيادة
Leading innovation is about creating the space
قيادة الابتكار تتمثل في خلق فضاء
where people are willing and able to do the hard work
يُمكّن الأفراد من أداء العمل الشاق
of innovative problem solving.
المرتبط بعملية حل الشكلات الابتكارية.
At this point, some of you may be wondering,
قد يتسائل بعضكم الآن:
"What does that leadership really look like?"
"كيف تبدو هذه القيادة؟"
At Pixar, they understand that innovation takes a village.
تدرك إدارة بيكسار أن الإبتكار يتطلب جماعة.
The leaders focus on building a sense of community
يركز القادة فيها على بناء حس مجتمعي
and building those three capabilities.
وعلى بناء تلك القدرات الثلاث.
How do they define leadership?
كيف يعرّفون القيادة؟
They say leadership is about creating a world
يقولون أن القيادة تتعلق بخلق عالم
to which people want to belong.
يرغب الأشخاص بالإنتماء إليه.
What kind of world do people want to belong in at Pixar?
ما نوع العالم الذي يود الناس الانتماء إليه في بيسكار؟
A world where you're living at the frontier.
إنه عالم حيث تعيش على الحدود.
What do they focus their time on?
علامَ يركزون وقتهم؟
Not on creating a vision.
ليس على إنشاء رؤية.
Instead they spend their time thinking about,
بدلاً من ذلك، يقضون وقتهم في التفكير بشأن
"How do we design a studio that has the sensibility of a public square
"كيفية إنشاء استوديو يشبه الميدان العام
so that people will interact?
ليتيح للناس التفاعل والمشاركة."
Let's put in a policy that anyone, no matter what their level or role,
لنضع سياسة تتيح لأي أحد مهما كان منصبه ومستواه
is allowed to give notes to the director
تقديم الملاحظات للمدير
about how they feel about a particular film.
حول رأيهم بفيلم معين.
What can we do to make sure
كيف نتأكد من أن
that all the disruptors, all the minority voices in this organization,
المشوشين، كل أصوات الأقلية في المنظمة
speak up and are heard?
صريحة ومسموعة؟
And, finally, let's bestow credit in a very generous way."
وأخيرًا لنمنح التقدير بطريقة كريمة للغاية."
I don't know if you've ever looked at the credits of a Pixar movie,
لا أعلم إن سبق لكم رؤية مكافآت أحد أفلام بيكسار،
but the babies born during a production are listed there.
لكن الأطفال المولودون أثناء الانتاج مدرجون هناك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
How did Bill think about what his role was?
كيف كان بيل ينظر لطبيعة منصبه؟
Bill said, "I lead a volunteer organization.
يقول بيل:"أنا أقود منظمة تطوعية.
Talented people don't want to follow me anywhere.
الموهوبون لا يرغبون بملاحقتي لأي مكان.
They want to cocreate with me the future.
يريدون أن يتعاونوا معي في خلق المستقبل.
My job is to nurture the bottom-up
وظيفتي هي رعاية التقدم التصاعدي
and not let it degenerate into chaos."
وتجنب تحويله إلى فوضى."
How did he see his role?
كيف نظر إلى دوره؟
"I'm a role model, I'm a human glue,
"أنا قدوة، أنا غراء بشري،
I'm a connector, I'm an aggregator of viewpoints.
أنا وصلة، أنا مُجمِّع لوجهات النظر.
I'm never a dictator of viewpoints."
ولست مديرًا لوجهات النظر."
Advice about how you exercise the role?
نصيحته حول كيفية ممارسة دوره؟
Hire people who argue with you.
وظِّف من يتجادل معك.
And, guess what?
وخمنوا ماذا؟
Sometimes it's best to be deliberately fuzzy and vague.
من الأفضل أحيانًا أن تكون غامضًا عن عمد.
Some of you may be wondering now,
قد يتسائل بعضكم الآن،
what are these people thinking?
عما يظنه أولئك الناس؟
They're thinking,
إنهم يعتقدون أنه:
"I'm not the visionary, I'm the social architect.
"أنا لست صاحب الرؤى أنا المعماري الاجتماعي.
I'm creating the space where people are willing and able
أنا أخلق المكان حيث يكون الناس مستعدين وقادرين
to share and combine their talents and passions."
على المشاركة بمواهبهم وشغفهم."
If some of you are worrying now that you don't work at a Pixar,
لو كان من بينكم من هو قلق لعدم عمله مع بيسكار،
or you don't work at a Google,
أو لعدم عمله في جوجل،
I want to tell you there's still hope.
أريد إخباركم أنه لازال هناك أمل.
We've studied many organizations
درسنا الكثير من المنظمات
that were really not organizations you'd think of
التي قد لا تكون تلك التي تفكرون بها،
as ones where a lot of innovation happens.
حيث تجري الكثير من الابتكارات.
We studied a general counsel in a pharmaceutical company
درسنا مستشار عام في شركة دوائية،
who had to figure out how to get the outside lawyers,
الذي كان عليه اكتشاف طريقة لإقناع المحامين الخارجيين
19 competitors, to collaborate and innovate.
المنافسين وعددهم 19، بالتعاون والابتكار.
We studied the head of marketing at a German automaker
ودرسنا رئيس التسويق في شركة سيارات ألمانية
where, fundamentally, they believed that it was the design engineers,
حيث يعتقدون أن مهندسي التصميم،
not the marketeers, who were allowed to be innovative.
وليس المسوقين، من يجب أن يكونوا مبتكرين.
We also studied Vineet Nayar at HCL Technologies,
كما درسنا فينيت نايار من شركة HCL Technologies،
an Indian outsourcing company.
وهي شركة تعهدية هندية.
When we met Vineet,
عندما التقينا بفينيت،
his company was about, in his words, to become irrelevant.
كانت شركته توشك أن تكون غير مفيدة حسب تعبيره.
We watched as he turned that company into a global dynamo of I.T. innovation.
وقد شهدنا كيف حوّلها إلى محرك عالمي للابتكار في تقنية المعلومات.
At HCL technologies, like at many companies,
في تلك الشركة، مثل العديد من الشركات،
the leaders had learned to see their role as setting direction
تعلم القادة أن يكون دورهم تحديد الوجهة
and making sure that no one deviated from it.
التأكد من أن الجميع يسير وفقها.
What he did is tell them it was time for them
ما فعله هو أنه أخبرهم بأن الوقت قد حان
to think about rethinking what they were supposed to do.
لإعادة النظر في الواجبات المناطة بهم.
Because what was happening is that everybody was looking up
لأن ما كان يحدث أن الكل كان ينظر للأعلى،
and you weren't seeing the kind of bottom-up innovation
ولم يكن أحد ينظر للابتكار التصاعدي
we saw at Pixar or Google.
الذي رأيناه في بيكسار وجوجل.
So they began to work on that.
فبدأوا بالعمل على هذا.
They stopped giving answers, they stopped trying to provide solutions.
توقفوا عن تقديم الإجابات والحلول.
Instead, what they did is they began to see
ما فعلوه بدلاً عن ذلك، أنهم بدأوا في رؤية
the people at the bottom of the pyramid, the young sparks,
الناس من أسفل الهرم، الشرر اليافع،
the people who were closest to the customers,
الأشخاص الأقرب للعملاء،
as the source of innovation.
باعتبارهم مصدر للابتكار.
They began to transfer the organization's growth
بدأوا في نقل نمو الشركة
to that level.
إلى ذلك المستوى.
In Vineet's language, this was about inverting the pyramid
بتعبير فينيت، كان ذلك يتعلق بقلب الهرم
so that you could unleash the power of the many
لإطلاق العنان لطاقات الأكثرية
by loosening the stranglehold of the few,
من خلال حل القوة الخانقة للقلة
and increase the quality and the speed of innovation
ورفع جودة وسرعة الابتكار
that was happening every day.
الذي كان يجري كل يوم.
For sure, Vineet and all the other leaders that we studied
بالطبع، فينيت وكل القادة الذين درسناهم
were in fact visionaries.
كانوا أصحاب رؤى.
For sure, they understood that that was not their role.
وبالطبع كانوا يدركون أن ذلك لم يكن دورهم
So I don't think it is accidental that many of you did not recognize Ed.
لذا لا أرى أن عدم تعرف الكثير منكم على إد كان مصادفة.
Because Ed, like Vineet, understands that our role as leaders
لأن إد، مثل فينيت، يدرك أن دورنا بصفتنا قادة
is to set the stage, not perform on it.
أن نُعِد المسرح، لا أن نؤدي عليه.
If we want to invent a better future,
إن أردنا أن نخترع المستقبل،
and I suspect that's why many of us are here,
وأعتقد أن هذا هو سبب وجودنا هنا،
then we need to reimagine our task.
فعلينا أن نعيد تصور المهام المناطة بنا.
Our task is to create the space
مهمتنا أن نخلق مساحة
where everybody's slices of genius
حيث يمكن للجانب العبقري
can be unleashed and harnessed,
لأي أحد أن يتحرر ويُدعم
and turned into works of collective genius.
ويتحول إلى أعمال من العبقرية الجماعية.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)